Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Copies of House and Senate bills and handwritten summary of bills concerning condominiums, apartments and housing considered in 1982 General Assembly, 1982., 37 items. (Box-folder 6:14)
  Series 78: Human Resources
- Material relating to work of Human Resources Subcommittee, 1981-1982., 14 items. (Box-folder 6:15)
  Including 1981 annual report of the Department of Rehabilitative Services, items from 16 December 1981 subcommittee meeting, and May 1982 correspondence between Bateman and Governor Charles S. Robb.
  Series 79: In Vitro Clinic
- Correspondence and enclosures and legislative documents concerning in vitro fertilization in Virginia, 1979-1981., 11 items. (Box-folder 6:16)
  Including letters from Life Amendment Pac of Virginia, the Fund for a Conservative Majority, and Virginia Society for Human Life protesting use of state funds for in vitro clinics and copy of bill and undated model bill regulating clinics.
  Series 80: Income Sur Tax
- Materials relating to local option income sur-tax, 1969-1970, 1982., 28 items. (Box-folder 6:17)
  Including 1970 letter from Newport News citizen suggesting the idea, handwritten speech and press release relating to Bateman' s introduction of bill embodying the suggestions, numerous legal opinions on the bill, including one from Virginia Attorney General Andrew Miller, and copy of the bill.
  Series 81: Industrial Revenue Bonds
- Industrial Revenue Bonds, 1952-1982. (Box-folder 6:18-20)
  See also Newport News Shipbuilding, series 125; and Port of Virginia, series 147.
  - Photocopies of Virginia Acts of Assembly, Assembly reports, and court decisions concerning Newport News Port Authority, 1952-1973., 20 items. (Box-folder 6:18)
    See also Peninsula Ports, series 81, 147.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and legislative papers concerning amendment to enabling legislation of Peninsula Ports Authority of Virginia (PPAV) to allow issuance of revenue bonds to finance Graving dock facility to be leased to Newport News Shipbuilding in 1974, 1952-1974., 44 items. (Box-folder 6:19)
    Items consist largely of correspondence of PPAV officials and lawyers, but also includes 4 January 1974 proposal for resolution, 1974 summary of PPAV enabling legislation, 1952-1974, and November 1973 report on industrial facilities financing in Virginia.
  - Memoranda and other materials concerning Peninsula Ports Authority of Virginia (PPAV), 1974-1978, and 1982 industrial revenue bonds, 1970-1982, n.d., 21 items. (Box-folder 6:20)
    Items include undated [1974] PPAV resolution authorizing issuance of revenue bonds for financing Graving dock facility, background material on PPAV financing, copy of The Virginia Bar Association Journal of January 1970, 1978 lease agreement between PPAV and Shipside Packing Company, Inc., and 1982 position paper on industrial revenue bonds by a Newport News law firm.
  Series 82: Insurance
- Reports on insurance pricing/ratemaking in Virginia, 1971., 3 items. (Box-folder 7:1)
  Including 1971 report prepared for Bureau of Insurance of State Corporation Commission and undated model bill by insurance lobbying group.
  Series 83: Interest Rate Legislation
- Interest Rate Legislation, 1972-1982. (Box-folder 7:2-3)
  - Correspondence and reports pertaining to interest rate and usury sections of Virginia Code, including Virginia Bankers Association (VBA) legislative agenda for 1972 Assembly session and VBA report on 1972 legislation, 1972-1975., 49 items. (Box-folder 7:2)
    Items consist mostly of correspondence between Bateman and John W. Edmonds III, counsel for the Virginia Bankers Association, in which Edmonds rendered legal opinions on interest rate statutes which Bateman then passed on to law firm of Jones, Blechman, Woltz, & Kelly, and of correspondence with Attorney General Andrew Miller.
  - Correspondence and other items relating to interest rate legislation, 1979-1982., 22 items. (Box-folder 7:3)
    Including 1980 analysis of Virginia legislation relating to money and interest, bills and amendments (1980) to allow renegotiable interest rates by savings and loans, and information from Virginia Retail Merchants Association (1982) urging deregulation of open-ended credit.
  Series 84: Intermediate Appellate Court
- Correspondence and resolutions urging establishment of Intermediate Appellate Court in Virginia in order to relieve burden on existing courts and two copies of proposed revision of Virginia Code to provide for court, January-February 1982., 6 items. (Box-folder 7:4)
  Series 85: Interstate 664
- Correspondence and resolutions urging completion of Interstate 664 from Newport News, Virginia to Suffolk, Virginia, 1978-1982., 27 items. (Box-folder 7:5)
  Including spiral-bound packet of documents from Virginia Peninsula Economic Development Council, statements from officials of Newport News, Hampton, Peninsula Chamber of Commerce, and Newport News Shipbuilding, who touted I-664 as a "boon to the economy and national defense."
  Series 86: Joint Legislative Audit & Review Commission
- Joint Legislative Audit & Review Commission (JLARC), 1979-1982. (Box-folder 7:6-15)
  - Administrative policies and procedures manual, undated, of Virginia Joint Legislative Audit & Review Commission (JLARC)., 1 item. (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Reports of JLARC special study on federal funds and impact on localities as authorized by House Joint Resolution 237, 1979-1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:7)
    Including December 1979 interim report and spiral-bound collection of material presented at 30 May 1980 meeting of JLARC subcommittee.
  - Materials relating to JLARC study of federal funds in Virginia, 1980., 22 items. (Box-folder 7:8)
    Including 11 August 1980 spiral-bound exposure draft, summary of findings and recommendations, and commentaries on draft from various state agencies and state universities.
  - Operational review by JLARC on Management and Use of Consultants by State Agencies, 12 May 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 7:9)
  - JLARC exposure draft on Virginia's General Relief (Welfare) Plan, along with undated summary of findings and state recommendations, 14 July 1980., 3 items. (Box-folder 7:10)
  - JLARC exposure draft on Virginia General Relief (Welfare) Program along with summary of findings and recommendations, 4 September 1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:11)
  - JLARC exposure draft on Virginia's General Relief (Welfare) Program, along with summary of findings and recommendations, 8 September 1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Report on Virginia's cash management practices by Marshall 0. Sokol Associates, Inc., including information on Federal Cash Management Program and Second Annual Management Conference, 15 September 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 7:13)
  - JLARC study of Title XX of 1974 (Federal) Social Security Act in Virginia, 1974-1980., 3 items. (Box-folder 7:14)
    Including 10 November 1980 JLARC exposure draft, 10 November 1980 staff briefing, and undated summary of Title XX benefits in Virginia.
  - Correspondence, memoranda and reports pertaining to JLARC review of general government and JLARC study of vehicle cost responsibility, 1982. (Box-folder 7:15)
    Items include Assembly resolution for general government study, copy of 9 July 1982 JLARC exposure draft on vehicle cost responsibility, and letters from officials of Virginia Railway Association and Virginia Highway Users Association debating findings of JLARC study. 30 items.
  Series 87: Joint Subcommittee to Study Virginia's Individual Income Tax Structure
- Joint Subcommittee to Study Virginia's Individual Income Tax Structure, 1967-1980. (Box-folder 7:16-22)
  - Background information, 1967-1971., 4 items. (Box-folder 7:16)
    Including 1968 study of estimated personal incomes in Virginia and 1967 and 1971 Virginia Income Tax Study Commissions on implementation of simplified tax system.
  - Materials relating to work of joint subcommittee, 1978-June 1979., 22 items. (Box-folder 7:17)
    Including joint resolution establishing committee, roster of members (including Bateman), agendas and minutes of first meetings, review of 1971 study, and statistical and background information furnished to members.
  - Correspondence suggesting changes in tax structure and copy of September 1979 Department of Taxation paper, Issues for Individual Income Tax Reform in Virginia., October-November 1979., 5 items. (Box-folder 7:18)
  - Agenda for and information presented at subcommittee meeting of 28 November 1979, including another copy of September 1979 Department of Taxation report, 1979., 6 items. (Box-folder 7:19)
  - Draft and final report of the joint subcommittee, December 1979., 3 items. (Box-folder 7:20)
  - Minutes and working papers of joint subcommittee, including draft legislation and reports on individual income tax structure in Virginia and around the U.S., 1980., 13 items. (Box-folder 7:21)
  - Working materials of joint subcommittee, 1980., 13 items. (Box-folder 7:22)
    Packet of information forwarded to members in September 1980, including minutes of meetings, draft legislation, and reports on taxation in Virginia and other states.
  Series 88: Judicial Nominations
- Correspondence, resumes and resolutions endorsing candidates for judgeships, 1979-1982., 29 items. (Box-folder 7:23)
  Including 1980-1981 committee for courts of justice of Senate and House of Delegates judicial selection questionnaire.
  Series 89: Juvenile Courts
- Reports of Juvenile Court-Public School State Task Force on relations between schools and courts, 1977-1978., 3 items. (Box-folder 7:24)
  Series 90: Juvenile Judges--Authority of
- Bateman's (undated) memorandum requesting state code, and photocopy of H.R. 774 (20 February 1978) also amending code's provisions on juvenile courts, 1978, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:25)
  Series 91: Juvenile Justices
- Bills, acts, reports, and addresses on various issues involving juveniles, 1977-1979., 20 items. (Box-folder 7:26)
  Including delinquency prevention and Youth Development Act (1977), bills regarding used or neglected children, child sexual abuse and pornography, and reports on interstate compacts relating to juveniles and juvenile courts in Newport News, Virginia.
  Series 92: Juvenile Justice Code
- Reports of March 1978 and October 1978 on impacts of the 1977 juvenile code revision after six months and one year prepared by Department of Corrections, 1978., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:27)
  Series 93: Kepone
- Kepone. (Box 8-9)
  See also Seafood Industry, series 169.
  - Kepone - Chronologies., 7 items. (Box-folder 8:1)
    Memoranda from state interagency Kepone Task Force, Governor and other agencies detailing chronology of Kepone problem and responses to it.
    See also Toxic Substance Act, series 198.
  - Kepone - Regulations and Reports, 1976-1980, n.d., 23 items. (Box-folder 8:2)
    Copies of emergency orders (with supplementary data, maps and chronologies), 1976, 1980, prohibiting fishing and crabbing in James River, copy of (undated) Kepone mitigation feasibility project, and 1980 report on control of toxic substances in Virginia.
  - Kepone - Testimony and Hearings, 1976., 4 items. (Box-folder 8:3)
    Transcripts of testimony of Governor Mills Godwin and Otis L. Brown, Head of Kepone Task Force, before U.S. Senate subcommittee, 22 January 1976, transcript of (anonymous) speech before U.S. Senate on the Kepone problem, and published copy of hearings before Senate Committee on Kepone Contamination.
  - Kepone - Task Force, 1975-1976., 13 items. (Box-folder 8:4)
    Synopses of proceedings of interagency Kepone Task Force, 1976, and synopses of costs of task force.
  - Kepone - General Correspondence, 1975-1977. (Box-folder 8:5-6)
    - Incoming and outgoing letters pertaining to Bateman's work on behalf of Virginia seafood industry, December 1975-November 1976., 54 items. (Box-folder 8:5)
      Most important (and voluminous) correspondence was with Otis L. Brown, state Secretary of Human Affairs and head of Interagency Kepone Task Force, Governor Mills Godwin, State Health Commissioner James B. Kenley, and with several toxicologists.
    - Correspondence and telephone messages pertaining to Bateman's work on behalf of Virginia seafood industry, November 1976-September 1977., 66 items. (Box-folder 8:6)
      Most important and voluminous correspondence was with Otis L. Brown, Governor Mills Godwin, Virginia Marine Resources Commissioner James E. Douglas, Jr., and Dr. William Hargis, of the Kepone Task Force.
  - Kepone - Congressional Correspondence, September 1976-March 1977., 106 item. (Box-folder 8:7)
    Bateman's correspondence with Virginia's congressional delegation. Bateman wrote each of Virginia's representatives and senators on 4 October 1976, 21 October 1976, and 3 November 1976 and 2 December 1976 briefing them on the impact of Kepone on Virginia's seafood industry and requesting their assistance in convincing the F.P.A. to raise allowable "action levels" of Kepone in seafood products. File consists of Bateman's letters, the congressmen's replies and attached replies to their letters to the E.P.A., and Bateman's letter of 26 January 1977 public meeting and enclosing a copy of Bateman's presentation at that meeting.
  - Kepone - Correspondence with Toxicologists., 7 items. (Box-folder 8:8)
    Handwritten drafts of Bateman's letter and questionnaire sent to independent toxicologists regarding Kepone "action levels," along with working notes and persons to be contacted.
  - Kepone - Report of Dr. Deichmann, 1976., 25 items. (Box-folder 8:9)
    Correspondence and reports pertaining to report on Kepone action levels by Dr. William D. Deichmann, toxicologist from University of Miami, including copy of 10 November 1976 report and background material on Deichmann.
  - Kepone - Seafood Industry, 1976-1977. (Box-folder 8:10-13)
    - Correspondence, bulletins and newspaper clippings regarding seafood industry's campaign to have permissible "action levels" of Kepone raised, and Bateman's work on its behalf, 1976-1978., 74 items. (Box-folder 8:10)
      Items consist of correspondence, July 1976-January 1977, between Bateman and officials of the Virginia Seafood Council and the National Fisheries Institute, lists of members of these organizations, handwritten notes from meetings, notes for preparation of Bateman's presentation, newspaper clippings on seafood industry's reports, and 1978 report on public image of Virginia seafood.
    - Correspondence, telephone messages and other materials relating to Bateman's solicitation of contribution for the Save Our Seafood (SOS) fund from Allied Chemical Corporation, makers of Kepone, July 1976-December 1976., 37 items. (Box-folder 8:11)
    - Correspondence, bills, receipts and other materials relating to Bateman's service on behalf of the seafood industry., 85 items. (Box-folder 8:12)
      Items include lists on contributions and expenditures from the Save Our Seafood fund, bill to seafood industry from a law firm, and bill, receipts,, long-distance telephone records, and time records from Bateman' s work for Virginia Seafood Council.
    - Multiple copies of three undated addresses by Bateman on the impact of the Kepone crisis on the seafood industry, including remarks at a briefing of Virginia General Assembly members and address [to Virginia Seafood Council?] outlining a strategy for marketing Virginia seafood, n.d., [ca. November-December 1976]., 10 items. (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Kepone -Handwritten Notes., 40 items. (Box-folder 8:14)
    Miscellaneous notes handwritten on legal paper, most undated, pertaining to Bateman's meetings or conversations with James Douglas, Otis Brown, Dr. Joseph Borzelleca, and representatives of Virginia seafood industry regarding Kepone action levels.
  - Kepone - Press Conference, 10 September 1976., 18 items. (Box-folder 8:15)
    Correspondence, news releases, statements, and newspaper clippings pertaining to Bateman's public criticism of presidential nominee Jimmy Carter for his statements on Virginia's Kepone problem. File includes letter of Bateman to Carter, 7 September 1976, in which Bateman calls Carter's remarks "a cheap shot born of ignorance," multiple copies of Bateman's remarks at a press conference, draft of statement from seafood industry representative affirming Bateman's opinion, letter and copies of remarks from former Lieutenant Governor and Jimmy Carter-ally Henry Howell, and copies of newspaper article on this feud.
  - Kepone - Presentation, 26 January 1977., 3 items. (Box-folder 8:16)
    Three copies of Bateman's presentation on behalf of Virginia seafood industry regarding Kepone action level at EPA public hearing, 26 January 1977.
  - Kepone - Action Levels - Commentaries, January 1977., 8 items. (Box-folder 8:17)
    Memoranda and transcripts of statements on Kepone action levels by Lee J. Weddig, of National Fisheries Institute of Marine Science, Dr. James B. Kenley, State Health Commissioner, an official of Allied Chemical Corporation, and others.
  - Kepone - General Assembly Action, 1971-1977., 16 items. (Box-folder 8:18)
    Legislative papers, January 1977, involving proposed amendment of Poisoned Food Provisions of Virginia Code, including copies of H.R. 1971 and amendment in the nature of a substitute for it.
  - Kepone- Material, 1980., 30 items. (Box-folder 8:19)
    Correspondence and notes relating to efforts to ease or lift fishing ban on James River, including Bateman's 2 July 1980 statement at public hearing in which he denied that Kepone posed a health threat to humans, 1 August 1980 letter from State Marine Resources Commissioner to State Health Commissioner urging reconsideration of fishing ban, Baternan's handwritten notes of 2 July 1980 hearing, and Bateman's 27 June 1980 letter to official of Virginia Seafood Council in which Bateman offers to represent seafood industry at future public hearings for a fee of $7500.00.
  - Kepone - Economic Impact, 1976., 11 items. (Box-folder 8:20)
    Reports on impact of Kepone on Virginia economy, including 16 January 1976 report and February 1976 EPA report, and several 1976 repots on economic impact of Kepone and on Kepone-related state agency costs by Philip Gabel, staff economist for State Health Department.
  - Kepone - Action Levels - Legal Memos, 1976., 3 items. (Box-folder 8:21)
    Legal memoranda on Kepone action levels, including 15 September 1976 memo from law firm (Truitt, Fabrikant, Bucklin, and Lenzner) retained by Virginia seafood industry, and 21 October 1976 memo, The Legal Effects of the Kepone 'Action Levels' prepared by firm representing Allied Chemical.
  - Kepone - Action Levels -EPA, 1975-1976., 30 items. (Box-folder 8:22)
    Memoranda and correspondence from officials of environmental Protection Agency, 1975-1976, regarding Kepone action levels and the health effects of Kepone.
  - Kepone - Action Levels - Testing, 1976-1977. (Box-folder 8:23-24)
    - Memoranda and reports, August-October 1976, by EPA and Food and Drug Administration (FDA) detailing procedures and methods for testing for Kepone, including 29 October 1976 EPA report, 1976., 14 items. (Box-folder 8:23)
    - Memoranda and reports pertaining to Kepone action level testing, 1977., 23 items. (Box-folder 8:24)
      Including EPA's 10 January report several drafts of (undated) seafood industry Kepone monitoring plan, and technical articles on Kepone testing.
  - Kepone - Toxicology, 16 items. (Box-folder 8:25)
    Memoranda and reports on carcinogenicity of Kepone, 1976-1979, including reports from National Cancer Institute and Environmental Protection Agency, and membership list of Society of Toxicology.
  - Kepone - Food Chemical News, 1976., 14 items. (Box-folder 8:26)
    Photocopies of excerpts from weekly publication Food Chemical News, August-December 1976, probably furnished to Bateman by Virginia Seafood Council.
  - Kepone - Miscellaneous Background Material, 1975-1977., 14 items. (Box-folder 8:27)
    Articles, bulletins and memoranda regarding Kepone, toxic substances and food and water safety, including photocopied excerpts from The Food In Your Future(1975), EPA-staff report on regulation of pesticides (December 1976), report on PCBs in food supply and other materials.
  - Kepone - Test Data, 1975-1976. (Box 8-9)
    - Results of tests of Kepone contents of James River and Chesapeake Bay finfish and seafood most presented in tabular form showing date and location of sample., 40 items. (Box-folder 8:28)
    - Results of tests of Kepone content of finfish and seafood in tabular form with graphs and maps, furnished by Virginia Institute of Marine Science, State Water Control Board, and other agencies, 1976-1977, 1979-1980., 29 items. (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Kepone - Computer Test Data, n.d. (Box-folder 9:2-9)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 33 items. (Box-folder 9:2)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay Fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 33 items. (Box-folder 9:3)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 26 items. (Box-folder 9:4)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay Fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 23 items. (Box-folder 9:5)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 30 items. (Box-folder 9:6)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 21 items. (Box-folder 9:7)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 19 items. (Box-folder 9:8)
    - Computer-generated data on Kepone content of James River and Chesapeake Bay fish, grouped as found in Bateman office files, n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Kepone - Test Data - Rock Study, 1979., 1 item. (Box-folder 9:10)
    Virginia Polytechnic Institute Rock Study, [1979]: a graphic and tabular report on Kepone levels in various types of fish and seafood.
  - Kepone - Newspaper Clippings, 1976-1979. (Box-folder 9:11-13)
    - Original newspaper clippings from Richmond, Newport News, Norfolk, and Washington, D.C. papers regarding the Kepone crisis and the seafood industry's efforts to cope with it. January 1976-February 1977., 55 items. (Box-folder 9:11)
    - Photocopies of clippings from Virginia Newspapers pertaining to Kepone crisis, 1976-1979., 52 items. Photocopies. (Box-folder 9:12)
    - Photocopies of newspaper articles pertaining to Kepone crisis forwarded to Bateman by various persons, 1976-1979., 45 items. Photocopies. (Box-folder 9:13)
      Including Virginia Marine Resources Commissioner James Douglas, representatives of the Virginia Seafood Council, and lawyers for the VSC File includes attached correspondence.
  Series 94: Kindergarten
- Materials relating to January 1981 bill to restore full funding to half-day kindergartens, 1981., 7 items. (Box-folder 9:14)
  Including copy of bill and messages and testimony of Edward W. "Ned" Carr, official of the Newport News School System and the Coalition for the Continuation of Local Option Kindergarten Programs.
  Series 95: Labor Laws
- Miscellaneous materials pertaining to Virginia labor laws, 1970-1980., 6 items. (Box-folder 9:15)
  Including Bateman's statement of 15 June 1970 regarding unemployment benefits for Newport News shipyard employees, and Virginia Employment Commission statement on House bill increasing unemployment payments.
  Series 96: Laetrile